[Music]
Stanford
University all right last time I started
to tell you something about how Quantum
field
Theory
um gives rise to a theory of the
particle interactions through an object
called the
Lan
I think that was not ch ably clear so I
want to go back through it a little bit
before starting to discuss the
details uh the details of particle
physics we're still thinking about
Quantum field Theory the basic technique
that I was that I was alluding to last
time is called the path integral method
of quantum
mechanics um and it is the most direct
root to Fineman diagrams to the theory
of particle interactions that are based
on finan
diagrams so let me just
uh try to briefly go through the basic
ideas which we started to do last time
but uh I don't think I was sufficiently
clear
anyway uh the path integral formalism or
method in quantum mechanics due to
findan is a generalization is the
quantum mechanical version of the
principle of least action so I just want
to remind you what the principle of
least action
is uh if we're talking about a particle
now I don't mean a particle from the
particle physics Quantum field Theory
point of view just a classical Newtonian
particle the motion of a classical
nutonian
particle from one point of SpaceTime to
another just very quickly is determined
by a l grangian l grangian is a function
of the coordinates of the particle
the time derivatives of the
particle and from the lran whatever the
lran is one constructs the action and
the action is an integral along the
trajectory of the particle of the lungan
for every trajectory whether it's the
true trajectory or not the true
trajectory from here to here by the true
trajectory I mean the solution of of
Newton's
equations from one space time point to
another SpaceTime Point whether or not
the trajectory is a solution it has an
action the integral of the lran along
the
orbit the classical principle of least
action is that the trajectory followed
by the particle through SpaceTime
minimizes the
action from that you can derive
differential equations and those
differential equations are called
Newton's equations
and uh I will assume that you know a
little bit about this idea of
action now the same idea applies to
classical field
Theory and the way the idea
works is for a particle for an ordinary
particle motion the legrangian is a
function along an orbit a function of an
orbit for a field Theory and of course
it's an orbit which connects some
initial configuration to a final
configuration for a field Theory the
equations of motion of a field Theory
classical equations of motion are also
determined from a lan the
lran is a function of whatever Fields
I'll call them generically just
fi and not just the time derivatives of
the fields but the space derivatives and
the time derivatives let's say
derivative of f with with respect to X
mu that's just a just a um shorthand way
of saying that the lran depends on fi
and derivatives of I one thing which is
required by the theory of relativity is
that the lran be a scalar that a
transform under lench Transformations as
a
scalar but that being said the lran can
be anything built out of fi's and
derivatives of fi okay what is the
action
imagine we have a region of SpaceTime
time as usual flows upward space is
horizontal and we have a region of space
time between an initial time and a final
time
okay then the action in this region the
action is the action in this region just
as the action for a partical trajectory
is the action from one end point of the
trajectory to another here it's the
action in a region of space between an
initial configuration and a final
configuration and the action is equal to
the integral over that region let's
write a d4x which means the time and DX
and d y and d z of this
lran so it's the total integrated value
of the lran over space and time whereas
for the particle is just an integral
over
time now what do you do what's the
analog of a starting point for the
particle a value of the field on the
initial surface here given not just one
field but all the fields in the problem
prescribing the values of the field on
the initial surface here and prescribing
the values of the fields on the final
surface you can ask is there a solution
of the equations of oh let me go back a
step forget that um yes is there a
solution
of whatever the equations of the theory
are which starts with a given initial
value of the fields at time T equals
zero let's say and ends with the fields
being something different at some later
time and the answer is the principle of
least action again the equations of the
theory are formulated by saying yes
there always doesn't
exist something in
between which is a correct solution of
the theory which has an given initial
value of the fields here and a given
value of the fields at the end point and
the correct solution of the fields in
here is the one which minimizes this
action one which minimizes the action so
the principle of least action gets
extended to a kind of
SpaceTime principle of least action
where the degrees of freedom in here are
Fields okay now let me very quickly
remind you what the quantum mechanical
use of action is how exactly you derive
the classical principle of least action
from the quantum mechanical version of
fineman's quantum mechanical version we
won't we don't really need to get into
here you can go look it up and any
anything about path
integrals but for a particle let's come
back to the particle motion for a
moment uh according to findan or
according to Quantum
Mechanics a thing that you might want to
calculate is the
amplitude is there anything wrong with
the value of a field returning to itself
no no no no more than the possibility of
the position of this thing return to
itself so how do you how do you go from
one space-time event to another
SpaceTime event why SpaceTime events
we're having values of fields here and
values of fields here well we're
integrating B4 X so there has to be some
D4
trajectory no the trajectory is replaced
by a history a history of the field from
the beginning to the end a history means
the values of the
fields all along here everywhere is in
here okay the idea of a trajectory
becomes a trajectory in field space
which means we have to
specify actually the four for the
coordinates as well as the the field
values to get an initial point to get an
initial Point well we're you're you're
you're specifying the
initial boundary condition or whatever
as field values field values all along
some initial surface you pick the
initial surface right okay in other
words you pick time whole field at some
crosssection it's a whole field along
some cross-sectional
yeah all right which is another way of
saying the the whole field at a given
instant of
time and the final configuration is the
whole field at some
later uh time and the question is is
there a solution of the theory whatever
the theory is which interpolates in
between these in the same way that a
trajectory interpolates from here to
here and the rule is minimize the action
that in that if carried out we we we did
this um number of classes ago but if
that's carried out the requirement of
minimizing the action leads to partial
differential equations for the fields
and those partial differential equations
are things like Maxwell's equations
things like Einstein's equations and so
forth all right so all right let's come
back now to the quantum mechanical idea
the quantum mechanical idea has to do
with
amplitudes amplitudes are things out of
which you construct
probabilities so for example you can ask
the question what is the amplitude that
if a particle is injected into the world
however it's injected in at A Spacetime
point x and
t what is the amplitude that if I look
for it at a later time let's say this is
at X X and time T what's the amplitude
that if I look at a later time let's
call it t Prime that I will find it at
position X Prime and T Prime so it's the
amplitude that if I start a particle at
this point close my eyes for a while and
then turn on a detector which looks for
the particle at a certain place the
amplitude for finding it there that
amplitude is a complex number that
depends on the initial point on the
final point it's a complex number whose
magnitude squared is the probability all
right that's the rule Square the
amplitude or multiply it by its complex
conjugate and that is the amp that is
the probability for the particle to go
from here to
here fineman's rule is the
following it says
take the action for any trajectory take
an arbitrary
trajectory and write down the expression
e to the I minus
I the action of the
trajectory we can just write it out it's
integral of now we're talking about
particles now integral of the lran
DT from one point to another point it's
a function of or functional of the
trajectory
and now actually there's a factor of H
bar in here a factor of H bar in here
that's where quantum mechanics uh comes
into it sum this or integrate it over
all possible
trajectories
well in non-relativistic quantum
mechanics you don't let them go backward
in time but all possible trajectories
which never loop back in with on
themselves in time
sum that over all the possible
trajectories for each trajectory it's a
complex number add them all up now how
do you add up such a thing it's some
complicated kind of integral but uh we
we needn't worry too much about the
details of how you actually calculate it
that according to Fineman is the
amplitude for going from here to here
it's the sum of all possible classical
roots
classical root does not mean a solution
of the equations it just means a
possible root it's the sum of all
possible Roots whether or not the
solutions of the equations of Newton's
equations of uh of e to the minus I *
the action measured in plun constant
units incidentally plunk constant has
units of action so this is simply the
action and units of the plunks constant
the E arises because the
because to go a little step involves a
something very one plus an act term and
the action you have to multiply these
yes all together right
exactly that's exactly right and the
other thing here is the
I the I is part of quantum mechanics so
I kind of say
yeah probabil that sum is the thing
whose square is the probability by
square I mean times it's complex
conjugate this sum could hardly be a
probability because in general it's
complex it's got an i in it if you
multiply it by its complex conjugate
that is the probability this is the
probability amplitude the complex thing
right so this is finman's formulation of
quantum mechanics and now it can be
extended to Quantum field theory in
Quantum field Theory the corresponding
question now we're not actually going to
formulate it this way because uh but
this is a correct way to formulate we're
going to we're going to fudge it a
little bit and uh make our way through
it
without uh without any rigor but the
same idea you start with an arbitrary
configuration of the
field all right so that's some initial
fi of x x now being just X and not
t an initial configuration of the
field and now you look at some final
configuration of the field let's call it
y Prime of
X these are two different functions and
you can ask what is the probability
amplitude that if I start the field at
some value and let the system go and
then detect the field at a later time
imagine you had some way of starting an
initial condition with a field being
prescribed at every point of space of
course that's an idealization you don't
have a chance in the world of doing that
really but uh you had some sort of
apparatus which allowed you to start the
field in an arbitrary
configuration Let It Go and then you had
another apparatus which detects the
values of the field at every point then
you can ask what is the probability that
if you start the field in a given way
that at a later time the field will have
some
value again that probability is
determined in terms of probability
amplitude and the probability amplitude
is again the sum over all possible ways
of interpolating the field between
initial and final all
possible way exactly what I said all
possible ways of filling in between the
initial State and the final state with a
field value at every
point of e to Theus I times the field
action that's the integral the X DT DX
Dy
DZ
d4x of the lran which is a function of
fi and the derivatives of
fi so you evaluate the lran at every
Point integrate it up that gives you the
action for a
particular let's call it a trajectory
it's not really a trajectory in any
ordinary sense but it's a history let's
call it a history better yet for each
history each possible history that you
can imagine it doesn't have to be a true
history a real history for every
possible history you can imagine there
is an action the action is itself an
integral but then you can sum this over
all possible histories and that is the
amplitude to start with a field value fi
and end with a field value for I prime
between these two trajectories here
okay that's the notion of a path
integral yeah I'm not concerned that
there an infinite number I'm not
concerned that they an infinite number
of paths but the action is going to be a
finite number for each of these P so
well it's a finite complex number right
yeah so how can that converge to
anything why is that not a
number um
no there are many many integrals well
okay you're
asking all right I I let me let me
phrase it let me phrase it a little more
strongly adding up an infinite number of
numbers well that's that's uh that's
nothing special I think what you're
pointing out is that each one of these
numbers is not only finite but has a
magnitude equal to one or or something
that is not decreasing it has a
magnitude equal to one right it's an
exponential of I times something
right so any number like this is a
number which on a complex
[Music]
plane not minimizing it you're summing
over all trajectory you're just sum
summing
[Music]
over all of these F amplitudes okay yeah
these things do do converge they don't
um they converge
because because of they oscillate they
all lie on the infite the they all lie
in the infinite on the unit circle not
on the infinite circle on the unit
circle and yet the integrals do
converge
uh that's a definition of delta function
for example there that's one example but
there are many
examples uh where integrals like this
converge um the kind of thing that can't
converge
well if you you have an infinite number
of numbers all of which are positive and
you add them up positive and bound it
away from
zero right you have an infinite number
of numbers all of them positive and
bounded away from zero of course that's
going to diverge okay uh in this case
you have numbers which can cancel over
here as one trajectory over here is
another trajectory over here is another
trajectory these are the amplitudes for
different trajectories
and this one cancels this one so it's
not hard for an
integral say if if they're equally
distributed around the unit circle then
you get zero yeah and in fact in fact
most of them except for a small fraction
of them they are that's right they tend
to cancel a lot the only trajectories
which tend not to cancel are the ones
near the classical trajectory we want we
don't have to discuss that now but that
is the way that you go from quantum
mechanics to classical Theory at least
in this uh
formulation if you look for the
particular trajectories where you have
the least
cancellation those are the trajectories
of stationary action this the
trajectories where the action is
minimum uh but that that's that's
another story this is the quantum
mechanical path integral
formulation that much of modern field
Theory basically all of modern field
Theory Quantum field theory is based on
all right now I'm not going to derive
The Next Step I'm simply going to State
The Next Step
but I wanted to at least explain to you
what this quantity is before I show you
how in practice it's used now when I say
in practice
this is a bit of an
oversimplification but not too bad not
too bad the last time we talked a little
bit about how the lran is used to
calculate processes particles moving
from one place to another particles
interacting when I say calculate
processes what did I really mean I
really meant calculate the
probability for an initial state to go
to a final state but there are two
distinct
ways to think about relativist well
about field Quantum field Theory one is
in terms of fields and the other is in
terms of particles we know that there is
this Duality between particles and
Fields we could ask a totally different
apparently totally different question
instead of asking suppose you had a
given field value here and you want to
know what the amplitude is for a final
field value we could ask supposing you
had some incoming particles quanta of
the field you express things in terms of
field quanta rather than in terms of uh
classical field
configurations supposing I told you that
the field
initially was in a state which was
described by a particular collection of
incoming particles incidentally when I
say the field I may mean a collection of
fields all right so I tell you not the
value of the field along here but rather
the particle content coming
in and I tell you what the particle
content is going out and I ask you
what's the probability that you went
from one particle content to another
particle content it's a question of a
similar kind of question but expressed
in terms of the particle
representation of quantum field Theory
rather than the classical field
configuration and the answer not
surprisingly involves exactly this same
object okay we talked about it a little
bit I think what I told you last time
not incorrect but it was a little small
piece of it I said what you do is you
took one I'll just remind you of
something I said and then I'm going to
say it again but in a more correct way
you take one plus the L grangian
remember what we did we said let let's
divide up into space time into lots of
little
cells it's hard to give meaning to
objects like this like this path
integral uh directly the way to give
meaning to it is to divide up space into
lots of little cells and instead of
thinking about continuous functions or
even discontinuous functions think about
a value of the field in each one of
these
cells all right that makes it more
concrete and then in the end you divide
you uh you let the size of the cells go
to zero so let's not let the size of the
cells go to zero let's uh let's keep
them finite like this what I told you is
that you take the quantity 1 plus the
lran in each cell in the I cell or it
elsi that's the value of the lran in
each cell and you multiply it
for all the cells remember I said that
if you don't it doesn't matter because
we're going to say it again the right
way this time
right uh and then you did we did
something with this to try to
calculate and I tried to show you that
there are pieces in here which describe
the propagation of particles the
collisions of particles we're going to
go back over it again CU it really is
Central all
right first of all I
missed being t tied I was not terribly
uh clear it's really 1 - I * the lran in
each
cell okay all right now 1 minus I one
what's one plus a small this is for the
moment imagine this is a small quantity
I shouldn't actually it's not one plus
the lran it's one plus the action in
each cell now the action in each cell
is the lran times the space times
um times the SpaceTime volume in each
cell all right SpaceTime volume is Delta
X Delta y Delta Z time delta T for each
cell Let's uh call that a small number
let's just call it the space-time volume
let's call it a to the 4th where a is a
small number all right so each little
cell is small so the action in each cell
is itself
[Music]
small because the cell is
small now one minus or 1 plus a small
quantity let's called 1 plus Epsilon is
an approximation
[Music]
to e to the
Epsilon e to the Epsilon
is this is approximately equal for small
Epsilon
but the exact formula is a power Series
in epsilon it's
1 plus Epsilon plus Epsilon 2 / 2 plus
Epsilon cubed over what comes next 3
factorial which is 6 3 * 2 *
1 and so forth and so on
so uh 1 plus Epsilon is approximately
for
small things equal to e to the Epsilon
but in fact it's more efficient and uh
and correct to really write something
different than what I wrote over
here namely this
thing let's let's think about what this
thing
is fact on Che to put an H bar in
a here
yeah all right I'll probably wind up
setting H bar equal to one as usual but
uh
right okay what is this
object all right
um this exponential here what's in here
we're going to imagine replacing not by
an integral but by a sum the integral
over a space and time here just imagine
that we've replaced it by the
[Music]
sum and what is it a sum of it's the sum
of the action in every little cell
right each when I replace
the sum the integral by a sum up in here
when I replace the integral by a sum up
in here what I'm really doing is just
adding up the action in all these little
cells now the thing about
a
exponential is that the exponential of a
sum is the product of
exponentials e to the A + B is e to the
a * e to B so this can also be written
as another way in another way if we get
the summation here for a minute that's
summing over pair paths before we do
that summing over histories what this
object is it's an exponential of a sum
so it's also the product of e to Theus I
over
HR a in the first cell e to Theus I over
HR action in the second cell a is action
e to Theus I over HR a in the third cell
and it's exactly this kind of product
product over all the cells not of
one minus I * the action but of e to the
minus I * the action they're close to
each other it actually wouldn't matter
which we used but uh uh in practice
but
um okay so let's
now consider
question okay all right so now having
this form here let's go back to
what let's forget particles for a minute
and think about fields and
reexpress the uh the path integral
idea so here we have a region of space
time that's been chopped up into tiny
little cells
enough all right what's the idea of an
initial condition the the idea of
initial condition is to start on the
first row of cells here and give the
value of the fields at every point in
there that's an initial condition or
that's the analog of an initial
condition a final condition is to
specify the fields in the last
row so the question then is what is the
probability amplitude that if the field
is specified in a certain way on the
first row and the field is specified in
the last row what's the probability to
go from one to another or the amplitude
the amplitude that if you start it a
certain way and let the system run you
will later find it in the final State
and the final State now means the field
in each one of these cells here
answer you
take eus I * the sum of the action in
all the cells but we now realize that
this is simply the product of e to Theus
I of the action in each cell we multiply
together the action in all of these
cells for a given history for a given
history for a given history for a given
history which means a given value of the
fields in each
cell
and we multiply them all
together we compute the exponential of
the action and then we sum it over all
ways of populating the cells with
Fields all possible histories means all
possible values of the fields that could
be in every cell with the exception of
the first row and the last row the first
row and the last row are fixed by the
initial and final
conditions all right in other words by
the Oh by the initial and final
conditions we don't look at the field in
the interior we simply start the system
and then detect it and the rule is sum
over all
possible uh field configurations that
could exist in
between so that has reduced this idea to
a discrete
form in which we see that what we have
here is this infinite product or or this
product over uh over actions all right
now let's uh
let's try to formulate some ideas about
particles instead of asking the
question what if we start with a given
field
configuration what if we start with a
given particle configuration and end
with a given particle configuration what
is the amplitude to go from one to the
other so I'll I'll I'll tell you how you
think about it and we're not going to
derive this we've talked about it a good
deal we've talked about the ideas as a
good deal we've talked about the fact
that fields are made up of creation and
Annihilation
operators uh and what we're multiplying
together here is functions of the
fields functions of the fields and
therefore function yeah I read somewhere
that someone thinks that field quanta
are not necessarily identified with
particles you're right you would
disagree with that well I'm not sure I'm
not sure who in what was the context
field Theory no no I'm not sure who said
it and what the context was
um uh but you you well give me a little
more to go
on the question was somebody said
something my grandmother probably said
it but that the field Quant in Quantum
field Theory are not necessarily part ID
identifiable
as um as as a particle the only thing I
could think of is that he was talking
about quirks
and of course in some sense quirks are
particles but in some other sense
they're never detectable as particles
because they can never escape from one
another that's the only thing I can
think of uh so quarks are the quanta of
the Quark field but they're never
directly detected as separate quarks um
uh well separated from other quarks
that's the only thing I can think of
that he might be speaking about well I
guess during during unary evolution
ution it doesn't
necessarily boil down to observables and
so you may not have particles that are
identifiable at intermediate
States I don't know what the um if you
accept the idea of a quirk as a
particle it's true that there's not a
onetoone
correspondence necessarily between uh
the fields in a theory and the particles
in in the theory
that's an idea which is true as long as
the coupling constants in the theory are
small okay
so um there is not necessarily A
onetoone
correspondence yeah I mean it is true
there are field
theories that uh for one reason or
another you wouldn't describe their
Quant as conventional particles but you
know at some level it's just a
difference between words uh if you
define particle to mean Quant then
there's no difference between
them they're
indivisible uh they uh they carry energy
and so forth um so for my money I would
call them particles but
uh but yeah when you talk about selling
over histories is there some limitation
what histories you they have of
continuous in some sense no no no in
fact they don't have to be continuous uh
first of all of course the idea of
continuity on a discrete space like this
doesn't quite mean very
much uh the field in the neighboring
cell is just going to be a different
value of the field the rule is the the
rule is divide the space into cells and
and in actual practice this is the way
Quantum field theory is defined you
divide the theory into
cells you some of all possible ways of
um of populating the cells with values
of the fields all possible ways no
restriction to things which are
approximately
continuous and in fact Quantum fields
are not approximately continuous they
jiggle a great
deal and
uh you sum over all the possible values
of the
fields and um that gives you your
empasis so in principle for each field
and each derivative you can assign
assign
it uh all possible values from minus
infinity to plus well you you don't
assign the derivatives separately from
the fields the derivatives of course are
related to differences of the fields in
neighboring boxes so you populate with
field values and then derivatives are
replaced by uh yeah and you can use
there are different um rules that you
might adopt
uh you might Define the derivative here
to be the difference of the field here
and here okay right that's yeah that's
that's that's a minor detail and U yeah
but but in any event you you you might
take the real line up and break it up
into small intervals but You' still have
a a sum over a countable number
of possible values of the field for one
for each field and if there were two
Fields then you'd be doing that over yep
by the by the field here I mean all of
the fields right so you would you would
give a value to each possible field in
the theory at each initial nasty looking
computation absolutely well so since
these are complex functions they're
analytic functions so
well the analytic functions of uh but
the relationships between the values of
the field have to have
to
um have to have to conform to you know
what you learn in complex variables you
know no no complex variables is about
the theory of analytic functions
analytic functions are extremely
smooth they're the smoothest functions
you can think of these functions do not
have to be
smooth they're they're complex valued
but they're not analytic functions
thei the field as functions of position
definitely not
they're uh they're uh on the average
highly discontinuous but uh I were to do
the if I were to do the computation on a
computer how how do I
know uh you know that will converge and
do all the right things yeah I mean how
how many different fields I have to
consider how many different different
assignments I have to okay so of course
this this by now is um a major indust
industory called lattice gauge Theory or
lattice Quantum field Theory lattice
because it divides the world into a
latus and this has been studied to death
how uh how to do these integrals in
practice um by now it is a very
effective tool but it took you know some
30 years to to develop the Computing
technology I was involved in it in the
very very beginning
the very very beginning I wasn't
involved in the computer technology of
it but uh setting up the rules for
lattice gauge Theory okay so there was a
history the first part of it was setting
up the rules for it and that took about
3 weeks and then something like 30 years
to develop the technology to compute
these things and you're right I mean you
know how do you know when you've uh when
you've sampled enough of the space okay
so there are uh and a lot of the wisdom
of it came from statistical mechanics
where you do very much the same thing
you calculate partition functions or
probability
distributions uh for this this
checkerboard here not a Quantum field
Theory it could be a um a uh a real
crystal lattice and you might be summing
over configurations of whether there is
or isn't an electron in each uh at each
site so a lot of the
methodology came from um the uh the
quantitative study of statistical
mechanic systems we have the same
question how do you know when you've
when you've sampled enough you know I
this is not the the subject of uh uh
tonight's lecture
so uh the answer
is the experts
know or they think they know
and they get good answers they get good
answers which agree with experiments so
it's it's it seems to work okay so let's
let's go back and remember that Quantum
fields are a shorthand for creation and
Annihilation operators and if we're
talking about let's say the product of
some fields in this box times the fields
in this
box that can represent the annihilation
of a particle in this
box and the creation of a particle in a
neighboring box so we might just
represent it by a particle moving from
one box to
another what kind of things in the
action here actually do correspond to a
particle moving from one box to another
so let me tell you there are things in
the action here which strictly speaking
are not associated with one box but with
a pair of boxes namely the derivative
terms the derivative terms I I was a
little bit Hasty here when I said you
multiply all these things together one
for each box as a little bit of a cheat
because there are terms in lran which
are associated with pairs of boxes so
really you can think of it as summing
over the boxes and summing over
neighboring pairs of boxes but that's
that's a detail which terms involve
pairs of boxes the terms which involve
pairs of boxes are things like the
derivative of f with respect whoops with
respect to
t squared the derivative of
f on a lattice becomes the D becomes the
difference of fi in neighboring
boxes so in here this derivative of f
with respect to T might really be
written as fi at point x X well five at
Point T and x minus fi at Point
neighboring time n x we actually have
secondes no second derivatives these are
first
derivatives never okay never bad
idea does real damage uh now what about
derivatives with respect to spatial
coordinates same thing it uh corresponds
to the to the difference
two neighboring points in space and then
the
instruction is to take 1/2 of the square
of the
derivative well 1 half of the square of
the derivative will have in it I just
want to focus now on the terms which
multiply
ftimes fire at a neighboring Point let
me just focus on those there's also
terms in here which multiply by by the
Same by the the value of the same point
but in particular there are terms in
this
Lan which multiply five at one point
time five at a neighboring point every
time you lay
down
um a term like this it represents the
motion of a particle from here to here
you can think of it that way
okay let's let's uh take let's
concentrate on these terms let's forget
the interactions in the L grangian these
are
simply these are called the kinetic
terms the quadratic terms in the L
grangian
they're things which are easy to deal
with and they do correspond to motion of
the particle from one point to another
let's look at this and let's include
only
those let's
we don't even need to write it in this
form let's just write it as e to Theus I
times the sum of all pairs of boxes over
all neighboring pairs of boxes I said
over all boxes but it's clear that's not
quite right we want to think of it as
sums over neighboring pairs of boxes of
things like five in one box time five in
a neighboring box I'll use the notation
x and x Prime to represent Neighbors on
the
lattice that's what goes into the
action or that's what goes into the
exponential of the action there are some
coefficients in front of it of course
but that's that's of secondary
importance and now we can expand out
this exponential let's see what's there
there's
1 - I
the sum of f
ofx f of x
[Music]
Prime and then things
like let's see what's the next
term I * I is minus one so it looks like
it's
minus summation of f ofx f of x
Prime squared
times another factor of the sum of f
of x f of x
prime or this could be PR of X prime xou
prime x triple
prime xou prime and XLE Prime are one
pair of neighbors this is another pair
of neighbors and I think I left out a
factor there should be a two factorial
downstairs I'm simply expanding out the
exponential here and what's the next one
well it has three powers of the sum four
powers of the sum and so forth okay
let's look at each term here the first
term
has something which involves a sum over
the
lce
of an annihilation of a particle at one
point creation of a particle at another
Point okay at a neighboring point the
next
term oh
incidentally the rule that I'm going to
tell you again I'm in the business of
telling you some rules now I'm going to
tell you some rules
now the amplitude for going from one
thing to
another the rule is you've got to close
off you must not have a
dangling end point a a dangling endpoint
can only dangle like that if you've got
an operation to put a particle into the
system a dangling end point for example
we're going to have diagrams which have
particles going from one point to
another if they end like this they're
illegal unless there's an instruction to
put a particle in at this point and to
take a particle out at that
point so end points like
this we will simply rule out as
things unless they correspond
to a specific instruction to put a
particle in at this point and take it
out since we're only putting particles
in in the initial State and taking them
out in the final State the only end
points would be allowed on the top and
the
bottom okay so let's let's take a
particular term here five of X and f of
x
Prime these are neighboring points on
the lattice and they correspond to
motion of a particle from one place to
another there's a sum of terms there
could be a term for a particle from here
to here a term for a particle from here
to here but none of these will
contribute unless of course there would
be one situation in which they would
contribute that would be of course if
this uh layered structure here was only
two layers high and we put in a particle
over here and took one out at the
neighboring uh point then there would be
a contribution to the amplitude of that
coming
from this term in the product 5 of x * 5
of neighboring X that would contribute
and it would contribute to the
amplitude basically the factor minus I
it would tell you that the amplitude to
go from one point to another was simply
minus I this coeffic ient here okay but
that's not very good if
this how do we get from here to here
okay how from here to here how do we get
a particle from here to here and
calculate the amplitude that if we put
in a particle over here that will detect
it over here for that we have to find in
this sum of products here we have to
have a term which will leave no dangling
ends okay let's take let's just take
this term
here this has a particle moving from X
to X Prime and then another particle
moving from X double Prime to x triple
prime are are you saying the second term
contributes only if the only only when
the initial and final state is are
adjacent this term here yeah yeah yeah
that's right this notation means
neighboring particles neighboring
neighboring boxes right here we have one
neighboring box and here we have two
other neighboring boxes yeah we
five first
term yeah the second term is yeah it
just means pick
to
neighboring and Su Over All possib
ilities sum this is a sum of all
neighboring pairs doesn't have to be to
the no no no no in general not but it
can be in fact this could even be the
same pair but it doesn't have to be some
of all of them all right so what does
this one do it moves a particle from X
to X Prime and this one moves a particle
from XP Prime to X Tri
Prime so one of them moves a particle
from here to here this is X Prime to X
double to X from X to X Prime and then
the other one moves a particle from here
to here that's X double Prime and x
triple prime let's
say obviously there's going to be
dangling
ends
unless well let's uh let's take this
case here where we only have three
layers if we only have three layers the
only way to avoid dangling ends is to
have the first particle
connected to the second particle like uh
sorry the first box connected to the
neighboring box and then this box
connected to this box there won't be any
dangling ends except for the dangling
ends which correspond to the initial
particle and the final
particles so if this was only three
layers
thick we would find a contribution
here namely where X Prime is the same is
XP
Prime that transports the particle from
the initial position to the intermediate
position and then from the intermediate
position to the final
position
um
okay what would be the amplitude then
associated with a particle going from
here to here at least corresponding to
this term it would be a 1 over2
factorial a minus
sign that would be it you read off the
coefficients and the coefficients tell
you the uh the amplitude thus far we
don't have a way to get from here to
here not with two steps anyway two steps
can
however if this was
only two layers thick we would have now
a weit to get from here to
here to go across the diagonal how do we
go across the DI diagonal we go again to
this second order term here the term
which has a two factorial in it and we
find the term which takes
us from X to X Prime and then from X
Prime from X to X Prime and then from X
Prime to uh from here to here and then
here to
here all what's that there are other
pths there are other other paths to get
to this yeah there's another path where
you jump from here first to here and
then up I don't think there's any other
besides
that yeah not with two oh not with just
two terms right okay but now there was
no reason to stop here with only two
terms Let's uh go on we can have three
terms three terms would
correspond to going from one box to an
adjacent
box well it would correspond to three
distinct uh
steps and if those three distinct steps
were to connected together into a chain
in other words in this sum of products
we found the term which took
us yeah we could we could come right
back
again that would contribute together
with the direct jump from here to here
would contribute to the amplitude to go
from this point to this point so you see
built into this prescription is
something like the original partical
path integral idea the amplitude to get
from here to here is the sum over the
amplitude to go from here to here and
the amplitude to go through another
route also this one back
here and eventually if you expand this
out to arbitrary order there will be a
term in there for every possible Ro
route that you can take to go from any
initial configuration to any final
configuration of that
particle so first of all just thinking
about a single particle moving in
SpaceTime this field lran contains
information about the
amplitudes to go
from now let's take an arbitrary
to go from any point to any other point
what you do is you add up all of the
possible ways of going
there and what is the coefficient for
each way of going there you read it off
the coefficient that multiplies that
particular term in this sum 1 over two
factorial 1 over 3 factorial some of
them have eyes some of them don't have
eyes remember that i^ squ is minus one
so some of them have eyes and some of
them don't have eyes and so in general
the uh the amplitude to go from one
point will be a complex number but they
can also go back and forth that's what's
new that's one of the things that's new
here that they can propagate up and down
and that's a feature of Relativity even
even even
say cells what's that even the same
thousand Oh indeed
you go back yeah all right let's talk
about going backward in
time you could think of let's here's one
that goes backward in
time you can think of this as either
allowing a new rule where particles can
go backward in
time or you can follow time forward and
say what really happened here is the
part parle move from here to here and
then a particle pair particle and
antiparticle in fact were
created the particle half of it going to
here and the anti-particle combining
together with the original particle to
annihilate think of it either
way but the rule now allows trajectories
which go
backward let's come back to this term
here
question in this formul since you have
factoral denominator does this mean that
you sort of have convergence in the
noral convergence
well the N factorials certainly help the
convergence but they're not enough to
make it converge
no no no no no no but the sum over
configurations doesn't have to converge
yeah this this part converges yeah and
it's this is going to be some finite
number of total configurations
considered
yeah okay um let's let me all right now
let's go on to a slightly different
problem we studied the particle moving
from one point to another now let's
suppose we put in two particles and we
want to know what the probability for
the two particles to go to two other
particles is in other words we want to
start and I'm going to
take the case where there are only two
layers for a moment there's the case
where only two layers for a
moment and I want to know the
probability that if I start a particle
over here it will get to here no if I
start two particles one over here and
one over here that they'll get to
here okay well come back to this term
now remember what this term did for me
before before it allowed me to hop three
units but that same term allows two
particles each to go one unit look at
it this can create a
particle this can annihilate it this can
create a different particle and
annihilate it this corresponds to
a graph where you start a particle in
here and goes to here that's this
factor and the other Factor instead of
taking the particle that's already there
and moving it over here it just takes a
totally new particle and moves it to
here okay so this same factor this same
term contributes both to the motion of a
single particle three boxes and it
contributes to two particles each moving
one box did I say that right yeah more
or less three boxes one two two boxes
yeah so there's a lot in here besides
just motion of a particle from one place
to
another it has information in it about
any number of starting particles going
to any other number of final particles
now in
fact particle number doesn't change as
long as we just take this into account
why not because every starting every um
dangling uh Endo
here well let's see um yeah it has to
end somewhere but uh well if you start
and end with different numbers of
particles then obviously something has
to happen well that would mean they have
to there has to be a dangling in
somewhere
um uh supposing I wanted to I mean I
can't how how would you get from one
particle to two particles what if I
start with electron and positron I could
end up with no particles well okay that
would be something all right that would
be something that would just be
something like
this two particles uh let's put another
layer in here yeah yes that that's true
that would correspond to an electron and
a positron for example annihilating each
other the only problem with it is it
doesn't conserve energy
so in fact when you added up all these
amplitudes you would get zero but uh but
but um so you have to yeah but yeah but
under certain circumstances if there was
an electromagnetic field to soak up the
energy uh yes you're right it would it
would it would have information in it
about an electron and a positron
annihilating right so there's just a lot
in
here there's a lot in here um but not
everything
not everything to find out the other
things that are implicit in the field
Theory there are other terms in the
lran now what you put in the lran is
determined by experiments and it's
really just a way of codifying the
results of experiments but what else can
you have in
lran uh we had the derivative
terms let's say f do^ 2ar
minus the derivative of f with respect
to X2 and y^2 and z^2 all that kind of
stuff that was the stuff that I wrote
down as F at one point time F at another
point at a neighboring point then there
are possibly other things that just
involve fi and not its derivative so for
example you could have things like 5^
squar remember what the coefficient
there's usually a 1/2 here that's a
convention
you remember what the coefficient of 5^
squ is the square of the mass of the
particle divide we should divide by two
that's again a
convention and if we included this term
here what that would
do it doesn't move a particle from one
place to
another
it absorbs a particle at one point and
emits it from the same point
right from the same point so it would
correspond to graphical constructions
where we would add a new
rule if a particle enters a region here
from one box to
another one of the terms that can act is
this Mass squar term it would
simply take the particle and do nothing
to it it would leave it in the same spot
then another term could come and move it
but it would weigh that particular path
with a factor of m
s every time this term acts it weighs
the path with another factor of m^2 in
the
amplitude so there would be terms where
no M squares
act where only these derivative terms
act in other words we in expanding this
product out we only have the derivative
terms that would be the theory of
massless particles
the theory of massive particles would
have a new rule that one of the possible
things that can happen at every step is
you may or may not just weigh that path
at that point with the m squ all right
so the mass term is another rule for how
you evaluate these paths these path
integrals another rule it's uh we we
don't have to get into detail the main
point is is that the mass of a particle
is
codified by another term in the lran
which is m^2 5 squared which weighs
paths in such a way that it knows about
their Mass all right but more
interesting is the more complicated
terms things like f squar let's put a g
sorry F
cubed V
cubed can do a number of things it can
annihilate one particle and create two
particles it can annihilate two
particles and create one particle it can
create three
particles uh it can annihilate three
particles all right so that's a new kind
of thing that can happen on this
checkerboard here in expanding
out the action expanding out the
exponential there might be additional
terms here for example GF cubed
when we expand out we can have not only
these products which take a particle
from one point to another but also
processes where particles are created
and
annihilated in threes either two in one
out two out one in or three in or three
out what that looks like on
here is for example supposing we have
several of these quadratic terms which
move particles in one cubic term what
can that look like well what it can
do is it can take a
particle moving it from here to here and
suddenly in that box we put a f cubed in
that
box it can absorb one particle and emit
to more now the next thing that could
happen is the two particles could
move through other boxes
but basically what it does is it takes a
particle absorbs it and creates two and
those two particles can be on their
way and this would then contribute to a
process where one particle came in two
particles went
out in fact you can make very very
complicated things you can make things
of Arbor let's go back to the one
particle going from one place to
another one particle going from one
place to another let me stop drawing
checkerboards let's just uh imagine the
checkerboard there uh one particle go
from one place to another can go
directly just a bunch of small hops a
bunch of uh these hops but also
something else can happen on the way at
some
point the cubic term could act if the
cubic term can act it can take that one
particle coming in and split
it split it into two and
then uh both particles move along
until another cubic term something
quadratic in the cubic terms something
with two cubic terms in
them
can create an extra particle and
reabsorb
it so in fact the actual amplitude to go
from one point to another by one
particle is not just the sum of simple
trajectories going from one point to
another through the through the
SpaceTime but is more complicated it has
infinitely more complicated it has
processes where the particle splits and
rejoins in other words where the
particle emits a second particle which
is then
reabsorbed an example of this would be
an electron moving along and emitting a
photon
and reabsorbing
it part of the amplitude for an electron
to go from one place to
another is through the process of
emission and absorption of a photon it
can get wildly more complicated of
course we have to add all of these up
the rule is add up the amplitude for
every possible way to go from the
initial state to the final
State you could
have several of these splitting and
joinings
you could
have things jumping across the uh the
gap between
particles and this can get arbitrarily
complicated uh from the point of view of
qu of electrons and photons things like
this could happen you know uh electron
goes through Photon emitted another
Photon emitted but even worse the
photon can break up into an electron and
a positron
but then the electron and positron can
exchange a photon between them all of
these processes come out of expanding
out the action like this and finding the
individual terms which do all of these
things if you want the amplitude for any
one of these processes you just go back
to what appears here find the term that
you're looking for and find the
coefficient in front of it it may or may
not have an i depending on whether it's
an even power or an odd power and it
will have some factorials and so forth
that will give you the amplitude for a
specific process but then the full
amplitude to go from one thing to
another is the horrendously complicated
sum of all these things right so you may
have certain things that happen in
multiple of those histories in what in
multiple of those histories you may have
similar terms which then the overall
amplitude for that process would be
actually from all the different history
yeah from all the different histories
going from the initial to the
final so there are two ways to think
about field Theory one is to think about
fields and think about histories as
initial values of the fields final
values of the fields and you sum over
all the values of the fields in between
and the other is this particle way to
think about it where the field is
replaced by a distribution of Quant and
again amplitudes for initial
configurations which means an initial
particular set of particles and a final
set of particles the basic processes the
basic underlying processes which happen
are governed by this lunian that is the
most important thing anytime you have
more than two Fields interacting you
have an interesting interaction process
where part particles can split and join
and so forth what would happen if you
had five to the 4th here which is a
perfectly good
interaction that would be someplace
where a particle for example could come
in and break up into three other
particles you know one to absorb the
initial state three to emit the final
state or it could be a scattering in
which two particles come along Collide
and two go off off anything that looks
like a Vertex with four particles all
together two in and two out or two in or
three in one out or so forth or just
four
out or four
in they're all governed by this
term and so forth and so
on
um let's see how are we
doing so that's the spontaneous arrival
of four particles at the final
State yeah except once again it would
violate energy conservation so if you
really worked it
out and um added up the amplitude from
every position where this could happen
every space-time position where it could
happen you would find out that uh that
it doesn't happen doesn't happen in
other words they all add up to
zero okay so processes which violate
energy Ty ically um uh all add up to
zero in these in these things energy or
[Applause]
momentum so so the conservation of
energy falls out of the doing the
calculation yes and the conservation of
same thing yeah and the conservation
yeah now we did we did some examples I
show you how integrating the vertex over
all time conserves energy how
integrating it over all space conserves
momentum them same thing is true here
integrating the position of these
vertices and the end points of these
things over all possible positions in
space and
time uh
will simply add up to zero unless energy
and momentum is conserved but apart from
the conservation laws everything that uh
that you can draw down will happen with
some Pro with some
probability right
now how could it possibly be that you
add up this humongous thing and the
answer doesn't come out
infinite well uh the answer is that
there are coefficients
here there are coefficients here these
are called coupling
constants particularly the coefficients
for the higher Powers here we could call
this G3 we could call this
G4 and the rule is in a diagram an ainan
diagram like this every time you have a
Vertex let's say with three particles
coming
together the amplitude contains a factor
of G G3 in this case so the more
complicated the diagram gets the more
powers of G that it
has each vertex gives you a power of G
if G is a small
number then each successive power of G
gives you a smaller and smaller
contribution and you have a chance that
the thing might be able to
converge the technical question of
whether it really converges or not is a
very difficult one but you can see that
you have a chance if G is a small number
if these coupling constants are small
numbers then the simpler the process is
in other words the fewer number of
vertices the bigger the contribution and
the larger the number of vertices the
more complicated the smaller the
contribution and you have a chance at
any rate at some sort of convergence to
an answer if the coupling constants are
large it means these series do not
converge and if they don't converge it
doesn't mean that the theory is is wrong
it just means you've chosen a naive uh
prescription for trying to work with it
but but in practice most of the quantum
field Theory most of the things we do
with Quantum field Theory are based on
the Assumption of small coupling
constants and under those circumstances
it's possible to to evaluate these find
not just evaluate them but add them up
and find out that the one with uh with
uh four vertices is much smaller than
the one with two
vertices so that's the name of the game
do color theory in the same way yeah
yeah we're going to talk about color
theory
[Music]
um now the next step is to name is to
write down the list of all
particles and to write
down either in the form of Lans or in
the form of Fineman
rules the Fineman rules and the Lans
have the same information in
them three identical particles coming
together let's say three bons that's 5
cubed particles going from one point to
another those are the kinetic terms the
quadratic
uh terms here so
the finan type
rules and the
lran are the same
thing and you can either describe the
World by specifying all the vertices in
incidentally the lines between one point
and another are called
propagators the uh placees where more
than one particle more than two
particles come together those are called
vertices vertices and
propagators right but they're as I said
they're just simply another Shand way of
describing the lran the lran is a
shorthand way of describing the
graphs uh so we would have stated all of
particle physics in a kind of dumb way
by simply writing down the list of all
particles writing or constructing or
even just expressing a Quantum field for
each
particle and then writing down a
lran for all those particles would
contain all of the interactions or we
can write down all of the particles and
simply specify what all the possible
vertices
are either way they come to the same
thing they're kind of a complete list of
everything that can happen once you know
everything that can happen you can start
thinking about calculating amplitudes
for particles to go from one place to
another particles to collide particles
to collide and
Scatter here's particles colliding and
Scatter two electrons colliding and
scattering just by a photon jumping from
one place to another right again lran
tells you how to calculate the amplitude
for each of
these and um
as I said it contains all the
information including symmetries
including conservation
laws uh so I think it's probably should
we write down the list of all elementary
particles so when you you write down a
finin diagram basically the bottom is
the initial configuration and the top is
that's right that's right the bottom is
the initial configuration of particles
the top is the final configuration of
particles and as I said
it is the kind of complimentary way to
think about field Theory Quantum field
Theory complimentary to the field
description where you would start with a
given field configuration and end with a
given field
configuration incidentally in some uh
sense the complimentarity between
particles and Fields is very much like
the complimentarity between momentum and
position uh these are two different ways
to describe the same reality
and there are uncertainty relations
between them if you know with Precision
the number of
particles then uh then you know that
there's uncertainty in the values of
fields if you know the values of fields
then there's uncertainty in number
particles so these are really two um uh
complimentary ways to describe the same
thing and uh the lran is useful in both
contexts
question uh the coupling constants are
those predicted by Theory or empirically
determined are there sometimes under
certain circumstances there are
symmetries which relate coupling
constants so this or that coupling
constant uh for this process might for
symmetry reasons be related to another
coupling constant for a different proc
process so some of them are related to
each other by uh by
symmetries but uh their values in
general
are simply come from experiment simply
come from experiment
um all right much of this if you really
go and learn about Quantum field theory
has its beauty it has it does have
elegance and beauty and so forth now
when we start writing down the list of
facts what particles there are what
their masses are what their coupling
constants are it's just a mess it's just
a very ugly mess with very little
coherence except the coherence that is
that that comes from
symmetries symmetries tell you
relationships between different kinds of
particles and their processes but a part
from the symmetries which are few and
not so
much uh it is a large number of random
facts about the about a somewhat
unmotivated uh uh collection of
different kinds of particles but still
you're pretty confident of the coupling
constants because if you once you
measure them you measure them if you
change it a little bit then you get
wrong answers oh absolutely no no no I
mean okay let's put it this way you have
too many particles which means too many
fields too many for any aesthetic
uh sense you have a lot of them a
hundred of them or something right a lot
of coupling constants which are just
more or less uh numbers pulled out of
experiment and a lot of masses which
range all over the map okay a few
relationships between
them uh but once you know them once you
know them that's it you can calculate
with great Precision anything about
those particles and anything about those
particles anything about quarks
electrons and photons and so forth means
Atomic physics or it means particle
physics it means Atomic physics it means
Nuclear Physics it means uh
chemistry and maybe it means biology
maybe so so the amount of input that
goes in is perhaps bigger than you might
like but the amount of output is uh is
huge question for for electron for
example how many of the G suban would be
G2 G3
G4 well how many G's are
there for electrons and protons in
electrodynamics one the electric
charge the electric
charge the H G3 there's no G3 and G4
well in a sense the electric charge is a
kind of G3 Sor the electric charge is a
kind of G3 the electric charge is the
coefficient in the amplitude
representing an electron coming in an
electron going out and a photon being
emitted right in terms of
symbols this diagram would be
represented by an
electron going out an electron coming in
and the field operator for a photon
which is a I'm not writing down the
details there are some po sorry some G
some um direct matrices but then the
numerical coefficient in front of it is
the electric charge in C certain units
certain dimensionless uh definition all
right now the only processes in Quantum
electrod Dynamics are the emission and
absorption of
photons from electrons that's all there
is well if there electron collision with
Aon for yeah electron collision with a
photon is just the simplest process
would be Photon absorbed I meant to say
proton oh
well protons are not usually considered
a part of the part of quantum
electrodynamics now you can think you
you when you do Quantum electrodynamics
you are doing Atomic physics you think
of the proton as a point infinitely
massive uh you don't think of it as
something described by uh by Quantum
field Theory you just think of it as a
nailed down heavy particle which never
[Music]
moves until you open up the theory of
protons and neutrons I mean but uh all
right so the the scattering by a photon
a photon by an electron this is the
first diagram but the electron is moving
at the almost the speed of light
relative to the
proton proton yes but right yeah that's
right um let's draw let's draw some
diagrams just to get some feel for what
kind of things we have to add up this is
the lowest order diagram that goes into
um into the scattering of a photon by an
electron there are two powers of the
electric charge so there's an e^
squared but this is the
amplitude the amplitude gets squared to
find the probability or the
cross-section cross-section is another
way of speaking about the probability
for the scattering all right so that
means that the whole
process the probability is proportional
to the electric charge to the fourth
the electric charge at least in suitable
with a suitable definition is a small
quantity the square of the electric
charge with again with a suitable
definition is about one well that's the
number which is 1 over
137 the fine structure constant so this
is proportional to the square of the
fine structure constant and so
scattering in Quantum
electrodynamics is a unlikely process of
a photon comes in and strikes an
electron what is the probability that it
goes right through it versus the
probability that it really scatters it
the probability that really scatters it
is governed by this e to the 4th and
it's a very small number now we have to
add all the processes that we can find
add them up to form a real amplitude
incidentally there's another one here
which looks like
this where
the final photon is emitted before the
initial photon is absorbed that's
another another process we have to add
them all but then we start adding more
complicated things let's uh focus on
here and we can add another
Photon in many ways uh this is not the
only way we could have to go from here
to here from here to here many photons
but how many powers of electric charge
does this have
this has four powers of electric charge
in the amplitude and eight in the
probability so this is even
weaker but then we can do even more
complicated things we can put a electron
positron pair in here each time we
complicate it we add two more powers of
electric charge so in Quantum
electrodynamics the expansion is
typically an expansion in powers of the
square of the electric charge every time
you add
another
complicating structure to ainan diagram
it's two powers of electric charge and
it means it's about
100 a couple hundred times smaller in
amplitude than the previous one that's
why when you add them up it looks like
it
converges because more and more
complicated they get the the weaker the
the uh probability from that particular
configuration incidentally
you don't Square this and add it to the
square of this and add it to the square
of this to find the
probability you add them up and then you
square that's the rule add and then
Square add and square that means there's
cross terms between
them in calculating the probability
these are called inter interference uh
terms so that's that's the structure of
quantum field Theory that's that's what
we do with it um the next issue as I
said we're now at the stage where we can
really start to sensibly talk about
particle physics we can name all the
particles we can specify their masses
those are the parameters in lanan here
that uh We've Spoken of and uh we can
write down the Lans governing them
partly from Theory partly from
experiment and discuss their
symmetries uh the symmetries can be
discussed by looking at the L grangian
we'll do that and uh we can write down
the standard model of particle physics
and discuss some of its
properties so I think we're
uh um off
to I think we we're set now to move
ahead and really discuss the world of
genuine real particles and what can be
discovered time instead of that M squ
you could had the Hig field and then
that would be
right that's we're going to discuss that
that's
okay what where are they in that
expansion oh they're here x and x Prime
could stand for two different
times that's how we managed to move
vertically
all right which is the term that
corresponds to the just
stand there's also some terms now this's
this from there are various terms where
the particle just stands still when we
wrote
down F of xus f of x Prime
[Music]
squared that had did have terms in it
like f ofx s and 5 x prime squ those are
terms where the particle stand still uh
the cross terms are the ones where it
moves so there are terms of the particle
stand still both from this and from Mass
term right
yeah
okay for more please visit us at
stanford.edu